Southwestern Mission Research Center records, 1965-1994 MS 443
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Southwestern Mission Research Center records 1965-1994
Collection Number: MS 443
Southwestern Mission Research Center
This collection contains materials documenting the activities of the Southwestern Mission Research Center (SMRC) from 1965-1994. This collection is comprised of SMRC daily operational documents including; correspondence, business records, conference information, publication information, and tour information. The bulk of the material contains correspondence either to or from Rev. Charles W. Polzer, S.J. focusing on activities of the SMRC.
3 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
None
Historical Note
The Southwestern Mission Research Center was created in 1965 mainly through the determination of Rev. Charles W. Polzer, S.J. It is a nonprofit organization which was originally set up for the purpose of locating for Father Kino’s grave and to conduct related research on this topic. After the discovery of Father Kino’s gravesite in 1966, the Center became dedicated to promoting, coordinating, and developing research studies pertaining to the Spanish Borderlands.
SMRC began publishing a Spanish colonial newsletter in 1967 to help bridge the gap between anthropologists and historians who were interested in the history of the southwest. In 1974 the Center started to offer tours of the Kino missions which introduced people to the history and culture of the Pimeria Alta, in the Sonora Desert of Mexico and Arizona. SMRC also sponsored the Gran Quivira Conferences from 1972-1988, and the conference of Spanish and Latin American Archivist (SPARCON) from 1984-1986. The center published numerous publications about the history of Pimeria Alta, the most popular being the Kino Guide I and II written by of Rev. Charles W. Polzer, S.J.
This Collection is organized into 5 series.
Series I: Conference, 1972-1988
Series II: Organization, 1965-1994
Series III: Publication, 1966-1996
Series IV: Research, 1966-1988
Series V: Tours, 1974-1991
The collection include financial records, meeting minutes, projects, SMRC tours information and other materials relating to the daily operation of SMRC. The materials focusing on specific conferences, such as Gran Quivira and SPARCON are contained in the series of the Conference, which includes the planning, invitation, correspondence, and conference schedules. The Board of director meeting minutes, miscellaneous correspondence, history of the center, and business financial records are arranged in the Organization series. The newsletter, books SMRC published and promoted, and newspapers collected by SMRC are under Publication series. Projects and proposals are included in Research series. All information related to tours is contained in Tours.
Kino, Eusebio Francisco, 1644-1711.; Polzer, Charles W.; Indians of North America -- Missions -- Southwest, New; South western Mission Research Center (U.S.).; Arizona State Museum; Spanish mission buildings -- Southwest, New.; Explorers – Spain.; Frontier and pioneer life – Arizona; Indians of North America -- Missions -- Southwest, New.; Explorers -- Southwest, New.
- Series I: Conference, 1972-1988
  Series note: This series is organized by conference title and arranged alphabetically. Each conference contains business correspondence, registration list, conference schedule information, and meeting notes. The first, Gran Quivira, is arranged by conference number then by dates. The SPARCON conference is divided to correspondences, papers and conferences at specific location.
  - Conference:Gran Quivira I-V, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Conference:Gran Quivira IV-X, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Conference: Gran Quivira XI-XVII, 1982-1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Conference: Lereto conference on Baja California and symposium, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Conference: SPARCON information, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Conference: SPARCON correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Conference: SPARCON research paper, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Conference: SPARCON USIA, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II: Organization, 1965-1994
  Series note: This series is arranged alphabetically. It contains organization related materials including Arizona Corporation Commission, Board of Director meeting minutes, correspondence, financial documents, historical documents and miscellaneous information.
  - Organization: Arizona Corporation Commission, 1965-1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Organization: Board of Director meeting minutes, 1987-1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Organization: Correspondence, 1964-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Organization: Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Organization: Correspondence, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Organization: Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Organization: Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Organization: Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Organization: Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Organization: Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Organization: Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Organization: Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Organization: Correspondence, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Organization: Correspondence, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Organization: Correspondences DRSW-SMRC, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Organization: Financial SMRC expense, 1968-1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Organization: Financial SMRC income and expense, 1971-1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Organization: Financial Tax return, 1968-1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Organization: Historical document, 1965-1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Organization: Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series III: Publication 1966-1996
  Series note: This series contains the books’ information that SMRC published and promoted, SMRC newsletters related correspondences, drafts and invoices, articles published on newspapers and magazines, and the copyright issue occurred on Kino Guide book 1.
  - Publication: Gallardo Affair (Book 1 copyright issue), 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Publication: Cabat book I-III, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Publication: Kino Guide I-II, 1972-1984 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Publication: Jose Velasquez/Ronald L. Ives, 1981-1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Publication: Newspaper article, 1974-1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Publication: Newsletter correspondences, draft and invoice, 1976-1996 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Publication: Stepchild + Tucson – Old Pueblo + Westerner’s smokes (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Publication: Tumacacori (plant) (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series IV: Research 1966-1988
  Series note: This series contains research related proposals, projects and miscellaneous materials.
  - Research: Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Research: Projects, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Research: Proposal, 1966-1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Series V: Tours 1974-1991
  Series note: This series is arranged alphabetically by the tours location. SMRC has conducted annual Kino Mission tour for different groups as well as the tours to different location for different people. This series contains California Baja tour, California Mission Tour, and Kino Mission Tour.
  - Tours: California Baja tour, 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Tours: California Mission Tour + Miscellaneous, 1975-1978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Tours: Kino Mission tour correspondence, 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Tours: Kino Mission tour correspondence, 1979-1988 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Tours: Kino Mission tour directories, 1978-1987 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Tours: Kino Mission tour financial report, 1986-1991 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Tours: Kino Mission tour promotional and newsletters, 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Tours: Kino Mission tour St. Benedict’s and SAH, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 16)